- 是珍女士吗 - 是
- Lady Jane? - Yes.
王后陛下即将到达
Her Majesty is just coming.
除非陛下要求你回话 你必须保持缄默
You are not to speak anything to her until you are invited to.
是
Yes.
- 陛下 - 陛下
- Your Majesty. - Your Majesty.
西摩女士 请将手按在圣经上
Mistress Seymour, will you place your hand upon this Holy Bible…
承诺并宣誓
And will you promise and swear.
忠诚 恭敬 谨慎地
to serve Her Majesty Queen Anne…
侍奉王后陛下
faithfully, honorably and discreetly.
承诺并宣誓汝之言行
And will you promise and swear that your conduct.
保持谦逊 贤良
will always be modest, virtuous and good,
始终恪守本分
presenting at all times a godly spectacle to others?
我承诺并宣誓
I do so promise and swear.
珍女士
Lady Jane.
陛下
Your Majesty.
国王驾到
The King.
- 陛下 - 陛下
- Majesty. - Your Majesty.
大臣阁下
Mr. Secretary.
我设法取得了一份
I managed with some difficulty to obtain a copy of.
凯瑟琳王后的秘密验尸报告
the secret report of the autopsy on Queen Katherine.
有何发现
What was discovered?
大部分内脏正常
That most of the internal organs were normal…
但在心脏外缘发现黑瘤
except for the heart, which had a black growth,
看来十分骇人
all hideous to behold, which clung closely to the outside.
何以致此
What could have caused it?
她的医生 深得我信任
Her doctor, who I trust completely,
他向我禀明 此症状
told me that such a growth was consistent.
显然是中毒引致
with the evidence of poisoning.
只要彻底检查遗体
Had the body been properly examined,
定会查到蛛丝马迹
traces of it would have been seen.
可怜的凯瑟琳
Poor Katherine.
非也
No.
无需为她祈叹
There is little need to pray for her.
她神圣的灵魂已永远安息
Her holy soul is in eternal rest.
但 我担心她的女儿
But… I worry for her daughter.
可怜的玛丽
Poor Mary.
稍后再谈
We shall talk later.
- 阁下 - 陛下
- Excellency. - Your Majesty.
听闻你的主上喜事临门
I hear your master is to be congratulated.
他从土耳其人手里夺得突尼斯
He has taken Tunis from the Turks.
陛下真是消息灵通
Your Majesty is very well informed.
皇帝陛下的胜利令人振奋
The threat of the Turkish invasion has indeed.
土耳其入侵的威胁已烟消云散
been lifted by the Emperor's victory.
和平指日可待
Peace will follow.
是否会遍及各地呢？
Ah! Would it follow everywhere?
是的 上帝保佑
Yes, pray God.
也许将来再也无需
Perhaps one day there will be no more need.
战争或战争警告
for war, or wars alarms.
与此同时
In the meantime,
请代我向皇帝陛下转达问候和祝贺
please convey my love and my congratulations to the Emperor.
转告他
Tell him that…
转告他 世上所有王公中
Tell him that, of all the princes in the world,
我最钦佩他
I admire him the most.
克伦威尔
Cromwell!
如今神圣罗马帝国皇帝挫败了土耳其
Now the Emperor has defeated the Turks,
他的军队可随时调头打我们
his armies are free to turn upon us…
我确信 他不久之前确有此意
and a while ago, I swear he would have done so.
但现在不会了
But no longer.
凯瑟琳一去
With Katherine's death.
他敌视我们的起因也不复存在
the cause of our enmity is altogether taken away.
我有意与他重修旧好
And I have a new desire to renew my friendship with him.
你去同乔普斯商谈
You will talk to Chapuys.
看看这份友谊要价几何
You will find out the cost of friendship.
遵命 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
改革进展如何
What of our reforms?
解散大型修道院的法案
The Bill for the dissolution of the larger monasteries.
将于下次国会议会期间提交
will be laid before Parliament at the next session.
甚好 克伦威尔
Good. Mr. Cromwell.
陛下
Majesty.
还有一事
Oh, there was something else:
我听闻你已有家室
I understand you have a wife and son.
是
Yes.
令郎的名字叫什么
What's your son's name?
格里高利
Gregory.
我曾有两个女儿
I had two daughters also. But…
但夭折了
they died.
带你的妻儿来王宫吧
You will bring your wife and son to court.
我愿接见他们
I should like to meet them.
是 陛下
Yes, Majesty.
陛下
Your Majesty.
陛下请随我来
If Your Majesty will follow me.
虔诚的人们
Good people,
欢迎
Welcome.
值此濯足节（耶稣受难前夕）之际
Here is the Queen's Majesty come,
王后陛下驾临
this Maundy Thursday,
为汝施舍 沐足
to give you alms and wash your feet,
- 我主保佑 - 主与你同在
- God bless you! - God keep you!
天主庇佑
God bless and keep you.
天主仁慈 庇护福佑
God in his mercy bless you and keep you.
瞧瞧
Will you look!
比原先那位王后给的多一倍
This is twice as much as the old Queen gave!
- 天主保佑你 - 天主保佑你
- God bless you. - God bless you.
教皇陛下
Holiness.
法国国王陛下觐见
His Royal Highness, the King of France.
陛下
Majesty.
你以朝圣者
You come to us.
及悔罪者的身份前来
as a pilgrim and a penitent.
理应受到上天垂爱
Surely you deserve heaven's graces.
我全心全意
With all my heart,
- 欢迎你来罗马 - 教皇陛下
- I welcome you to Rome… - Holiness.
教会的发源地
The Mother of our Church,
当其他人离经叛道
When others fall by the wayside,
追慕虚荣和贪欲
through vanity, avarice or lust…
你依然对教会和真理
you remain loyal to us,
忠贞不二
and to the truth of Christ.
如同孩子对待父亲一般
As a child to a father,
我在此向您表明
I say to you here,
神圣教会的众位红衣主教们作证
in the presence of all these princes of our Holy Church,
我愿不惜性命侍奉您
that I would gladly lay down my life in order to serve you,
任您差遣
and in whatever way you choose.
我决意颁布绝罚诏书
I have decided to carry out the Bull of Excommunication.
将英王亨利逐出教会
against King Henry of England.
父亲本该想尽办法
A father must always seek.
试图去原谅他的孩子
for ways to forgive his children,
但亨利对我们及我们的信仰
but Henry's crimes against us.
所犯下的罪行
and against our faith.
罪孽之深 无法原谅
are too profound to forgive.
非但如此 他既无悔过之心 也无悔过之意
Moreover, he shows no repentance, no contrition.
千真万确
It's true.
英王向来
The King of England has always been.
最难以相处
the most difficult friend to bear in the world.
他历来反复无常
He is continuously capricious.
既然如此
In which case,
我确信可以指望你来执行诏书
I am sure I can rely upon you to execute the Bull.
- 教皇？- 我的孩子
- Holiness…? - My son,
想必你意识到
surely you realize:
如果我将一国国君逐出教会
If I excommunicate a fellow prince,
那么这位君主
then that prince.
不仅被神遗弃
is not only separated from God…
也被上帝的所有子民遗弃
but also from the communion of the faithful.
他的统治将不再有效
His rule becomes invalid.
推翻他是天命所归
And it is a religious imperative to overthrow him.
你是强大的天主教君主
You are a great Catholic Prince.
你拥有军队 舰队
You have armies. You have ships.
火药枪械
You have guns.
作为圣父
So I ask you, in all humility,
我谦卑地请求你
as your Holy Father…
进攻英国
Will you invade England?
铲除变节者
Will you remove and kill the apostate.
令该国重归正道
and will you return that country to our common faith?
西摩家族古老而有趣
The Seymours are an old and interesting family.
对法战争中 约翰爵士同国王并肩战斗
Sir John fought beside the King during his French campaign.
他膝下有二子
He also has two sons:
爱德华和托马斯
Edward and Thomas.
听闻长子稳重冷静
I hear the first is steady and cold,
小儿子则轻率鲁莽
the other rash.
但二人皆野心勃勃 贪婪十足
But both are ambitious, and greedy.
他们虽然都宣誓效忠
Though they have all taken the oath,
但仍不能确信他们是否
what is not yet known is how honestly.
已与旧信仰彻底决裂
or completely they have renounced the old religion.
希望不久之后 我们即可揭晓答案
It is something we must hope, before long, to discover.
如果我们可以呢？
And if we can?
那么 他们的野心
Then, the tide of their ambitions.
将会逐渐消失殆尽
can be turned, and will ebb away,
而我们也可以从此耳根清静
and we shall hear no more of them.
启禀阁下 皇室大使求见
His Excellency, The Imperial Ambassador.
大使阁下
Your Eminency.
欢迎之至
You are most welcome.
请坐
Please be seated.
您真客气 大臣阁下
You are most gracious, Mr. Secretary.
正如我所说 国王陛下殷切地希望
As I told you, His Majesty is most desirous.
能与皇帝结成联盟
to make an alliance with the Emperor.
我也认为这场结盟
And I believe also that such an alliance.
能给国家带来巨大利益
would be greatly to the benefit of this country.
我已与皇帝商议过此事
I have communicated with the Emperor.
他也迫切地寻找手段
He, also, is eager to find a way.
缔造全新而稳固的联盟
to make a new and strong alliance.
为显诚心
And to show his good will,
他愿意劝说教皇
I can tell you that he is willing to persuade His Holiness,
保罗陛下 取消对国王的
Pope Paul, not to publish the sentence.
绝罚
of excommunication against the King,
不然这可能导致国王 王位不保
which would have deprived him of his throne.
我相信国王陛下
I am sure His Majesty would wish to express.
定会对您主人感激不已
his immense gratitude to your master.
我们能做什么回报呢？
And in return?
眼下
In the circumstances,
他挚爱的姑妈
after the death of his beloved aunt,
英国王后凯瑟琳已薨逝
Queen Katherine of England,
皇帝陛下愿意
the Emperor is prepared to offer the King.
支持
his support.
国王与安妮·波林的婚姻
for the continuation of his marriage to Anne Boleyn.
但前提是
But on condition.
国王必须宣布玛丽殿下
that the King declares Princess Mary.
为其合法继承人
to be his legitimate heir.
我承认 从各方面来说
I accept this is, in many ways,
这都是皇帝陛下
a very generous concession.
所做出的一个慷慨让步
on behalf of the Emperor.
他希望国王能够理解
He begs the King to understand it is as far.
这是他所能做的最大让步
as he is prepared to go.
我一定会向国王陛下转达这个提议
I will certainly put the proposal before His Majesty.
在你赞同下？
With your approval?
阁下 即使我赞同
Even with my approval, Excellency,
这也绝非易事
this may not be easy.
- 她真漂亮 - 谁？
- She's pretty. - Who?
珍·西摩女士
Lady Jane Seymour.
- 她是新进宫的 - 看一下
- She's new at court. - Here.
若汝沮丧无比 摆脱欲念
"If thou wilt mighty be, flee from the rage.
彼念残酷之极 希冀汝可远离
of cruel will, and see thou keep thee free.
肉欲奴役之污秽羁绊
from the foul yoke of sensual bondage."
我喜欢「肉欲奴役之污秽羁绊」
"The foul yoke of sensual bondage". I like that!
那你根本就没明白
Then you don't understand it.
也不知道被欲念驱使的残酷
or how cruel the will that drives it.
直至你见识肉欲奴役的果实
Until you see the fruits of sensual bondage.
在悬索上摆动
swinging from a rope.
- 是珍·西摩女士吗？- 是的
- Lady Jane Seymour? - Yes.
请见谅 有一位朋友在那边等您
Forgive me… but there is someone over here,
他希望能私下和您说两句
a friend, who wishes a word with you. In private.
- 哪位朋友？- 这边请 女士
- Which friend? - This way, my Lady.
珍
Jane.
国王陛下
Your Majesty.
我只请求你一件事
I ask you only one thing:
允许我侍奉你
That you allow me.
仰慕你
to serve and worship you.
如同兰斯洛特骑士对待格温尼维尔那般
As Lancelot served and worshipped Guinevere.
温文尔雅的女士
Sweet gentle Lady,
你可以成全我吗
will you let me so?
我可以
I will.
我可以亲吻你的手吗
May I kiss your hand?
亲爱的
My Lady.
你认识他们吗
Do you know them?
谁？认识谁？
Who? Know who?
西摩一家
The Seymours.
我见过爱德华
I may have met Edward,
那位长子
the eldest son.
他是个冷血动物
He's a cold fish.
其他人我不了解
I don't know about the others.
你怕他们？
Are you afraid of them?
父亲认为他们暗中支持玛丽
Father thinks they may be secret supporters of Mary.
玛丽啊玛丽
Ah, Mary, Mary…
真是可惜
It's a pity.
她没能陪母亲一起入土
she's not keeping company with her mother.
他们说她又病了
They tell me she is ill again,
而国王为了安慰她
and that the King has given permission for her removal.
同意免去她照顾伊丽莎白的繁务
from Elizabeth's household, for her comfort.
这只是出于怜悯之心 别无他意
It's an act of kindness. No more than that.
不 他喜欢她
No. He's fond of her.
过去曾是 现在依然是
He always was and he still is,
尽管当着我面 装作另一个样子
though he pretends differently to my face.
她的病情如何？
How ill is she?
就我所知 十分严重
Very. So I am told.
发着高烧 还不时地呕吐
With a fever and constant vomiting.
那蒙上帝恩典
Then, with God's good grace,
我们也许再也勿需干预她的事了
we may not have to meddle with her after all.
国王说要侍奉你？
The King has offered to serve you?
是的 父亲
Yes, father.
意料之中
I am not surprised.
这说明他喜欢挑战
And it means he does not seek an easy conquest!
他的爱意已经萌芽
He has formed an affection.
但更重要的
What's important is that.
是如何令他的爱意持久不绝
it should be carefully and assiduously nurtured.
我必须规劝你 无论国王的话多么有说服力
I must urge you not to submit yourself.
你都不能轻易服从
or yield your virginity to the King,
或献出自己的处女之身
however forceful his persuasions.
珍不需要那些有关
Jane does not need to be lectured.
贞操或谦逊的说教 爱德华
on the need for virtue or modesty, Edward,
因为那些品德是她与生俱来的
when she possesses them in her nature.
尽管如此 我们仍需考虑
Still, imagine what it would mean for us,
如若国王真的爱上她
as a family,
对我们家族意味着什么
if he did grow to love her.
我很肯定 朝堂之上
I am certainly aware there are.
有人希望另立新后
some at court who would like the Queen replaced.
等等
Wait!
我以为…
I thought…
你们是说要我取代现王后吗
Are you saying that I should be Queen instead of her?
你愿意吗
Would you like to be?
亨利爵士 跟我说说
Tell me, Sir Henry,
你和玛格丽特女士订婚了吗
are you engaged yet to Lady Margaret?
没有陛下 我…
No, Your Majesty. I…
我目前还没有向她求婚
I have not so far asked for her hand.
我的天啊 朋友
For God's sake, man!
她很年轻
She's young.
而且…
She's…
她会为你养育许多孩子 我知道的
She will give you more children, I know it.
我也知道国王陛下 但是…
And I know it, Your Majesty. But…
我曾结过婚 必须承认
I was married before and, I must confess,
我更喜欢单身的自由
I rather like the liberty of not being married again.
我理解
That I can understand.
你知道吗 亨利爵士
You know what, Sir Henry?
你在追求一位年轻的女士
You're courting a young lady.
而我…
and I'm…
我们应该再比一场马上枪术
We should joust together again,
就像以前一样
as we used to.
你总是在比武场上英姿飒爽
You always did grace the tiltyard.
我们往往要大战好几回合
We ran many courses against each other.
折断许多长枪
and broke many lances.
我们应该再比一次…
We should do it again…
你来组织吧
and you can organize it.
越快越好
Soon.
陛下
Majesty.
亲爱的 怎么了？
Ah, sweetheart! What is it?
你去哪了？
Where have you been?
我告诉过你
I told you.
我要开会
I had meetings.
- 枢密院的事 - 开到现在？
- Privy Council matters. - Until this hour?
是的
Yes.
国王的风流韵事不断
The King's affairs never sleep.
那你自己的呢？
And what of your affairs?
我的？
My affairs?
你刚从别人的床上回来
You have just come from another's bed.
不许否认
No. Do not deny it!
好吧 我不否认
Very well. I shan't.
更糟糕的是… 你不是因为
What makes it worse… is that you have not.
另一个女人而抛弃我
forsaken my bed for that of another woman,
而是另一个男人
But for another man.
我的上帝
Oh God! Oh my God!
我的上帝 果真如此
Oh my God! It's true! Oh, my God!
太恶心了
It's disgusting!
罪孽 这是违背上帝的
It's a sin. It's a sin against God.
这是违背世俗常理的
A sin against nature.
实践之人将遭天谴
And those who practice it are condemned.
而永坠炼狱
by the Gospels to live forever in purgatory.
我的爱人 有时候
Sometimes, my love,
我觉得和你在一起
I think that with you.
已经是如同身处炼狱了
I'm already condemned to live in purgatory!
献给你 我的夫人
Here, my lady.
你有一位好丈夫
You have fine husband.
沙福克公爵得分
Point for the Duke of Suffolk.
先生们 请重整长枪
Gentlemen, renew your lances.
王后陛下没来观看今天的比赛吗
Is Her Majesty not attending the tournament today?
没有 显然她担心比赛的激烈
No. Apparently she's worried that the excitements.
会影响到她未出世的儿子
of the tournament might harm her unborn son.
或者说是她期望的儿子
Or so she supposes it to be.
就我而言 我希望她
Personally, I hope she did not.
拜访的不是上次那位占星师
visit the same astrologer as before.
珍女士…
Lady Jane…
国王陛下
Your Majesty.
我正要上马比武枪术
I am about to go and joust.
不知是否有幸
Would you do me the honor.
可以允许我佩带你的信物
of allowing me to wear your favors?
沙福克公爵得分
A point to the Duke of Suffolk.
国王陛下
His Majesty the King.
已加入比武名单
has entered the list and will now joust,
并很乐意地
à la plaisance,
与亨利·诺里斯爵士比试枪术
with Sir Henry Norris.
好样的 查尔斯
Well done, Charles.
- 你表现得很棒 亲爱的 - 谢谢
- You hold on, my love? - Thank you.
让一让 让一让
Move, move!
他死了吗 他死了吗
Is he dead, is he dead?
让其他人来帮忙 你靠边
Let others help him. You can't.
把他小心移至
Take him with all care.
帐篷内
into the pavilion,
让我可以更好地诊治他
where I may serve him better.
为他祈福吧
And pray for him.
- 西摩 波林 - 大人
- Seymour! Boleyn! - Your Grace.
夫人 夫人 夫人
Madam! Madam! Oh Madam!
玛琪 怎么了？发生了什么事？
Madge. What is it? What's happened?
- 玛琪 发生了什么事？- 夫人
- Madge, what's happened? - O Madam,
国王比武时落马 摔伤了
the King has fallen from his horse and been crushed.
他们…
They…
他们说他可能会死
they say he is likely to die.
马克…
Mark…
告诉我这不是真的
Say it is not so.
不不不…
Oh no, oh no, oh no…
不是真的
Please no!
我的上帝 告诉我这不是真的
Oh god! Please, say it is not so…
他的心率很弱
His heart is very weak.
我不知道他是否还能苏醒
I don't know if he will come back to us.
您会给他放血吗
Will you bleed him?
我觉得不需要 大人
I don't think so, your Grace.
我不认为这对他有什么助益
I do not see it would help him.
陛下的生死
His Majesty.
现在只能听天由命了
is now in the hands of God.
我们赞颂你 主
Confitebimur tibi deus.
我们称颂你的名…
confitebimur et invocabimus nomen tuum.
- 我们这要去哪 - 回白厅去
- Where are we going? - Back to Whitehall.
你难道意识不到吗
Don't you understand anything?
在这紧要关头 一切都有可能分崩离析
In such a crisis, all could disintegrate.
所以中央一定得先稳住
So the centre has to hold.
必须由我们来稳住
And we must hold it.
大臣阁下 来自多佛的信函 阁下
Mr. Secretary. A letter from Dover, sir.
大臣阁下 大臣阁下
Mr. Secretary. Mr. Secretary.
- 有消息吗 - 杳无音讯
- What news? - There is no news.
国王仍旧没有生还的迹象
The King still shows no signs of life.
自事故发生到现在多久了
How long since the accident?
将近一个小时了 大人
Almost an hour ago, Your Honor.
神啊 我们称谢你
Confitebimur tibi deus.
我们称谢你 因为你的名相近
confitebimur et invocabimus nomen tuum.
人都述说你奇妙的作为
Narrabimus mirabilia tua.
我到了所定的日期 必按正直施行审判
Cum accepero tempus ego iustitias iudicabo.
大臣阁下 该怎么办啊
Mr. Secretary. What is to be done?
我正准备 万一国王驾崩了
I am making preparations, in the event of the King's death,
在阁下的许可下 为伊丽莎白公主加冕
for the coronation of the Princess Elizabeth with your lordship's approval.
她虽未成年
She would be in a minority,
但由其母后监护
but under the worship of her mother.
并由您来出任护国公
and yourself as Lord Protector.
您给玛丽小姐派卫兵了吗
And have you posted a guard on the Lady Mary?
港口关闭了吗
And closed the ports?
尽在掌握中
All that is in hand.
同时我也派人去准备召开国会紧急会议
As are preparations for an emergency recall of Parliament.
呸 昔时国王可一直不用国会
Bah! King's had no need of parliament in the old days!
此一时彼一时啊 大人
These are not the old days, my Lord.
您知道 我禁不住要想
You know, I cannot think,
国王驾崩
whether it would be a bad thing,
到底是好事 还是坏事
or a good thing, if he died.
因为 作为护国公
For, as Lord Protector, you would,
事实上
ipso facto,
你就相当于英格兰国王
be King of England.
陛下 陛下？
Majesty! Your Majesty?
查尔斯
Charles.
谢天谢地 陛下还活着
Oh thank God. He's alive!
好了 大家先出去 出去
C'mon gentlemen, out, out!
此为何物
What's that?
陛下跌落马下而安然无恙
We must be grateful that his Majesty.
我们应心怀感激
took no hurt in his fall.
是啊 谢天谢地
Yes, thank God.
但这意味着你顺利产下太子之事
But it means that the safe production of a son.
变得愈加刻不容缓了
from your womb is more than ever imperative.
所以我恳求
So I beg you to be.
你能小心翼翼 善自珍重
always careful with yourself.
不要用力 别兴奋过度
Take no exertions or excitements.
将自己封闭起来
Shut yourself away.
尽可能的远离世事
as much as you can from the world.
我希望能有办法
I wish there was a way I could remove.
把西摩小姐从我的侍女中赶走
Mistress Seymour from among my ladies,
可我不敢 我怕触怒龙颜
but I dare not. I think it would anger the King.
这正是我所担心的
This is what I mean!
如果你为这些鸡毛蒜皮的小事焦虑不安
If you fret about such little matters.
你的烦扰或许会危及到你腹中的胎儿
then your thoughts may poison the child inside you.
对我来说
It is not.
这并不是鸡毛蒜皮的小事
a little matter to me.
目前来讲是的
It is for now.
过阵子
Afterwards,
只要你满足了国王最大的心愿
when you have given the King his great desire,
到时候你想怎么处置她都行
then you will have all the power to deal with her as you like.
试想 我就是传达天主之意的天使
Think that I am the angel.
前来传达
come down to tell you.
你怀上圣子的消息
that you carry the Christ child in your belly.
- 那是什么 - 由于陛下落马
- What is it? - Because of the fall.
导致您腿上的旧伤口再次开裂 形成溃烂
this old wound on your leg has re-opened, and an ulcer has formed.
- 能治愈吗 - 绝对没有问题 陛下
- Can you heal it? - Oh most certainly, Majesty.
不过暂时需敷上些药
But for now you must wear a dressing.
把腿包扎起来
and have the leg bound up.
虽然陛下依旧年轻气盛
Though Your Majesty is still a young man,
但今非昔比
you are not as young as used to be.
昔时
In those days.
陛下在马上长枪比武
you would able to joust a whole day.
一整天下来都不觉得累
and not feel the effect.
我来给你的女儿传送国王谕旨
I have a message from the King, for your daughter,
当面私授
and for her ears alone.
珍
Ah! Jane.
- 大人 - 珍小姐
- Your Grace. - Lady Jane.
陛下要我把这封信送给你
His Majesty is pleased to send you this letter.
还有这个钱包 他希望你能收下它
And this purse. He commends you to accept these gifts.
它代表着陛下的心意
in the spirit in which they are offered.
真高兴看到陛下康复了
I am so happy you're well.
我是如此惊恐 不知所措
I was so alarmed, so afraid.
我又何尝不是啊… 一想到我的愚行
So was I… when I thought that through my foolishness.
- 可能导致胎儿流产 - 你的愚行？
- you might lose the child. - Your foolishness?
我以为还能像年轻时我行我素 实在大错特错了
It was a mistake to think I could behave as I used to.
无论如何
In any case,
那些无忧无虑的日子已经一去不返了
those carefree days are gone.
我们的女儿被带入宫廷
Our daughter was brought to court.
人人都对她赞叹不已
And everyone admired her.
他日定是绝色美女
I think she will be a great beauty.
那是毋庸置疑的
Of course she will.
有其母必有其女啊
Look at her mother.
陛下会去请求法国国王重新考虑联姻事宜吗
Will you not ask King Francis to reconsider his refusal?
要是伊丽莎白的婚事
If we delay much longer.
再拖延下去的话
to find a good marriage for Elizabeth,
恐怕闲言碎语会更甚今日
people will talk, even more than they do already.
玛丽都还没有订婚
Why do you talk of Elizabeth,
为什么你要谈伊丽莎白的婚事
when Mary is not yet betrothed.
你当然更该关心你的合法女儿啊
Surely you have more of a care for your legitimate daughter?
查尔斯
Charles!
她说什么了
What did she say?
她把信和钱包原封不动地退了回来
She returned the letter unopened, and the purse both.
她说在世上她珍视荣誉
She said that she has no greater treasure in this world.
胜过一切
than her honor,
还说如果你真要赐予她金钱的话
and that if you wanted to give her money, she praise you might do so.
莫如在她体面地婚嫁之际
when she has made an honorable marriage.
在此事上她表现得十分谦卑 非常得体
She has behaved herself in this matter most modestly.
帝国大使阁下求见
His Excellency the Imperial Ambassador.
- 阁下 - 我在寻思您是否
- Excellency. - I wondered if you had put.
已向国王陛下转达了皇帝的提议？
the Emperor's proposal to the King?
确切地说 没有
Not exactly.
我衷心希望
I wish with all my heart.
我们能够很快达成一致 然而
that we could reach a speedy accommodation. However,
在玛丽小姐
in the question.
合法子嗣这个问题上
of legitimizing the Lady Mary,
存在一巨大阻碍
there remains one great obstacle.
你指的是王后？
You mean the Queen?
我知道她痛恨皇帝是凯瑟琳侄儿的事实
I know she hates the Emperor as Katherine's nephew.
据悉
They say.
当她得知皇上挫败土耳其的消息时
that when she was told of his victory.
她表现得
over the Turks, she looked like a dog.
有如丧家之犬
being thrown out of a window.
我们该怎么做
But what can we do?
如果我们前进的路上
If there is an obstacle.
有了障碍 阁下
in our path, Excellency,
我们就得找个办法绕过去
we must find a way around it.
珍女士
Lady Jane.
陛下
Majesty.
我请求你走近些
I pray you come closer.
再近些
Closer still.
过来 坐我腿上
Here, sit on my knee.
别怕
Don't be afraid.
我重视你的名誉
I respect your honor,
相信我
believe me.
往后
And in the future,
我只会在你家人在场时 与你见面
I will only see you when other members of your family are present.
我只是现在很想见你
I just had to see you now.
是 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
你的信物救了我的命
Your favor saved my life.
- 不 - 千真万确
- No… - Yes.
当我躺在那时 你的影像突然浮现
As I lay there, your image came to me,
然后我就在誓言中醒来
and I awoke with this promise.
我该怎么说呢
What should I say?
我可以吻你吗 珍
Will you let me kiss you, Jane?
再来一次
Once more.
天哪
Oh, my God!
天哪 天哪 这算什么啊
Oh, my God! Oh, my God! What is this?
这算什么
What is this?
正当我身怀六甲
Just when my belly is doing its business,
就让我看到你们在此卿卿我我
I find you wenching with Mistress Seymour.
嘘 亲爱的 珍 你先走吧
Hush, sweetheart. Jane, you had best leave.
你为什么要这么做
Why are you doing this?
你为什么非得这么做
Why did you have to do this?
- 噢 - 冷静
- Ah! - Peace.
不 不 不
No, no, no, no…
别
Stop!
别这样
Stop it!
别哭
Stop.
一对杰克…
Two knaves…
一对Q 一张K
Two queens and a king.
你赢了
You win.
你说我是不是该去看看她… ？
Do you think I should go and see if she…?
不用了 让她好好睡觉吧
No. Let her sleep.
怎么了 陛下
What is, Your Majesty?
- 胎儿… - 天哪
- The baby… - My god!
吾儿啊
My boy!
快去叫人来帮忙
Get some help.
- 快 - 不 不
- Hurry. - No… no…
不 不 不 啊
NO, NO, NO… AAAH!
你令我痛失儿子
You have lost my boy.
损失之巨大
I cannot speak of it,
令我难以言表
the loss is too great,
但我终于明白了
but I see now.
上帝是不会赐我男性子嗣的
that God will not grant me any male children.
等你起床了
When you are up,
我再跟你谈
I will speak with you.
这也不能全怪我
It is not all my fault.
这事你只能怪自己
You have no one to blame but yourself for this.
看到你和珍·西摩在一起
I was distressed to see you.
让我痛心欲绝
with that wench Jane Seymour.
因为我对你的爱
Because the love I bear you.
至深至浓
is so great.
看你爱上了别人 我心都碎了
It broke my heart to see you love others.
我说过了 等你好了
I said I will speak with you.
我再跟你谈
when you are well.
不
NOOO!
私下的谣传原来是真的
It's true what they have whispered.
我假装两耳不闻
I shut my ears to them,
可现在我知道了 谣传是事实
but now I know it to be true.
由于受到巫术盅惑
I made this marriage.
我结下了这段婚姻
seduced by witchcraft.
有鉴于此
And for that reason.
这段婚姻无效
consider it to be null and void.
上帝不容
And the evidence is that God.
我们生下男性子嗣
will not permit us.
便是铁证
male issue…
所以现在我相信
so now I believe,
我彻底相信了
with all my heart,
我定要另择妻室
that I will take another wife.